so one of the questions that people who
come to the Hermitage ask most
frequently is where to begin with
reading the
discourses is there a particular order
and are certain discourses more suitable
to begin with than
others now if someone asks you a
question like that then how would you reply
to give a very technical
answer U one thing worth mentioning is
that the DGA Naya has
the by proportion it has the most sutas
addressed to
householders so that is one
consideration MH though maybe not most
important so what would be to your mind
the most important consideration
well it depends what people are coming
to the practice for MH often times
times
the the starting point that at least I
had the reasons I became interested in
the dhama I've learned need to change over
dhama I've learned need to change over
time
so
for me just reading as many as possible
and kind of getting a taste for what
they were was important mhm others may
not have so much of
a others might not need that
so depending on people's
proclivities that would
be worth taking into account but of
course the
something worth mentioning is that in
the sutas there's this distinction
between people who have Right View and
those who don't mhm and perhaps
explaining some of the
indications in the sutas that might let
you know oh is this addressed to
somebody with or without Right View
right so toally about this the
discourses are records of conversations
right people approaching the Buddha and
other awakened beings and asking
them their questions and their
difficulties so is there a single
discourse where two people who do not
have Right View are having a
conversation so the chief value of the
discourses then to start with is that is
that there's always at least a no
disciple or else an arat appearing on
the scene in order to clarify certain
matters and this is why the collection
of nikayas stand out from other writings
let's put like that otherwise it would
just be a collection of ordinary
conversations and that doesn't really go
anywhere now then there is the
possibility that Noble ones are giving
instructions to those who do not yet
have a Right View and there's the
possibility that Noble ones having a
conversation among 10 themselves
basically and now you are saying that it
is good to keep in mind that there is a
distinction between those who have Right
View and those who do not now how is a
newcomer who is about to dive into the
discourses going to find out whether
there's a conversation between two Noble
ones or
not and why should that
matter what what is the attitude of
someone who into discourses now that we
have introduced this
distinction think it's also a matter
of becoming clear what is right you and
not and and it's a very wide very open
discussion since
um it can be discussed over this matter
for a long time without having a a common
a long time without having a a common
point of uh of
you depending depending on how one can
read the text because all this maybe has
to be
mentioned the the text can be the the
poan can be read
in uh or interpreted in different
ways and and then each way pretending to
have the right
view yes so in the end someone needs to
check within their own experience yes
which means what what is let's go one
step back what is the attitude of
someone who approaches the
discourses if they coming to it for the
first time yeah well that
they for example you're talking about two
for example you're talking about two
Noble ones having conversation they
shouldn't assume that they are in a
position to understand what is being spoken about
to understand what is being spoken about
so they shouldn't um assume that this
applies to me for example you know
anapanasati or
these Sati
panas um that is a fatal error to to
assume uh that what I am reading my
interpretation of what is being written
is correct and that I have I'm I'm in a
position to practice now
because um that is undermining your
ability to question the assumptions that you're
to question the assumptions that you're
bringing to this
interpretation exactly so if someone
already assumes so if someone assumes
that all the discourses are on the same
level so to speak that they equally
apply app to everyone and that those
instructions and those teachings and
those contemplations that they can at
once put that into practice and
obscuring the fact that the right view
is something to be
acquired not by making some big donation
or by performing an esoteric ceremony of
some sort but by understanding these
formable tws directly for
oneself if that is
overlooked then that's actually an
obstacle for coming to see the DH if if
if somebody think have already
understood but has in fact not been
understood then it will prevent them
from understanding what needs to be
understanding what needs to be
understood so the attitude has to be
what the the attitude is I am reading a
text and I don't yet know what this is
about and so reading a text then is a
it's not about accumulating information
but about questioning one's own views
and assumptions and checking whether
that is in accordance with the with the
noble views that are expressed in the
discourses right are we going to say all this to
right are we going to say all this to
people who come here and ask where to
begin with reading the
discourses yeah exactly yeah that is
what we should be saying now if we have
introduced this distinction between
those who are of Right View
and those who are not and we see that it
is important to start out by saying one
doesn't have Right View and so this is
something to acquire suppose somebody
accepts that and then they're going to
read the discourses then what's the next
thing they should be looking
for well your question from a little bit
earlier about how do you know what the
context is is this two Noble disciples
or one no disciple one ordinary person
how do you know so what what comes to
mind for that is usually if it's
addressed to monks and it just kind of
leaves it at that no other
elaboration that's
generally to that's generally a
conversation between Noble disciples or
the Buddha addressing
because um that that's a good indication
yeah in the discourses conversation
between monks are nine out of 10 times
between those who are all over right
view um nowadays the situation is
different but if somebody is studying
the the discourses there that okay can
we say anything more than
this sometimes I'll just flip to the end
of a sua before reading it just kind of
see how it plays out because sometimes
it is like oh magnificent and you know
and it says the dam arose that means
that at the beginning of the
conversation they didn't have right view
but at the end they acquired it so those
are pretty valuable sutas CU that's like
okay this is addressed to somebody
without the Right View MH and the entire
point of the conversation is here's the
Right View yes so there are a number of
discourses you are saying where somebody
actually breaks through so to speak to
the right understanding and if we have
agreed that newcomers are not yet to
Right View then those are the kind of
discourses they want to be looking into
first and understand those first because
there's valuable Clues there as to what
leads to seeing the D directly for
oneself right those discourses where
somebody actually breaks through to the
right understanding that's one kind of
discourse there there are a dozen or two
such discourses in the nikayas now is
there another type of discourse that
is on that same level so so to speak the
kind of stock phrase that frequently
appears in the
sutas that people who are new should be
looking out
for the gradual training
or well yeah
although yeah yeah yeah that's actually
true that's gradual training but there's
also this stock phrase where it says
here an unau ordinary person who has no
regard for Noble ones and has not known
and regards things and then there comes
a
description of how people who are not of
Right View are regarding things whether
it be agregates or sense bases or other
aspects of their experience which is
then contrasted with how a well
instructed Noble disciple who knows and
sees the dhama regards things and there
are quite a number of those and it's
often a stock phrase so that's another
set of
discourses which directly
contrast contrast the understanding
between those who are not a d View and
those who
are and so are we saying that would be
good for somebody who wants to find
access into the discourses to start
looking for those as well yeah I haven't
thought about that
but yeah that's probably a good
way to approach it
yeah but um I
mean yeah I think inevitably there's
going to
be even in that what in that approach I
think it's just very important to say
that that uh it's incredibly difficult
that uh it's incredibly difficult
to to Really
um with with all of the views that uh
exist today that that are so prominent
today scientific view the religious
views um that yeah it's the sutas are so
Broad in their phenomenological
descriptions that it's incredibly
difficult to to see what they're saying you in a
to to see what they're saying you in a
sense yeah so yeah I mean you can you
can say you know start with these
discourses or the yes but um so yeah so
now that we have given some indications
that there are different kinds of
discourses that's what we said right
where someone gains the Right View and
these talk phrases we were just talking
about suppose we leave that for now and
we're going to discuss somebody's
attitude towards those discourses and
you just mentioned scientific View and
religious view now if somebody is a
scholar or an academic and they are
concerned with writing papers and they
happen to take an interest in early
Buddhism and you know it's publish or
perish so you know there's pressure to
put material out there um if that's
their background attitude towards
reading those discourses then is that
practically going to make any difference
for them are they are they going to gain
right view if if if if they're opposing the
view if if if if they're opposing the
text with that intention yeah so they're
coming to the text with that context
which is obviously not a wholesome one
if well the publish or Parish attitude
for example there's obviously craving
involved in that um but or financial
incentives or whatever but that's
putting that aside um even even if those
those weren't there to approach it in a
scholarly way um yeah it's it's not the suitors
way um yeah it's it's not the suitors
are they require authenticity self
transparency you know that that's you
know that's what the precepts are that
that's why
you have to yeah take them on so can we
make explicit what is then the
difference between what we now call a
scholarly attitude and an authentic
attitude like why is a scholarly
attitude not going to be beneficial in
terms of the goal of the real practice
what is what's the obstacle there what's
not seen in that
attitude it's uh horizontal
it's the approach of uh uh taking
in a lot of
information and then uh using it to
build up uh argumentations or uh
um
this uh bring up uh exp
explanations in a sense of of
um yeah putting one one notion after the
other whereas
[Music] the the authentic if I'm right as
the the authentic if I'm right as
a
approaches to go in in the in the in the
experience itself and and uh to
to to find out or to uh
in through
introspection to inquire what's uh how
the the the human mind is
uh is working if I can say but I
would what we were discussing before of
the attitude attitude I would say I
would like to say uh it's um it's also
important to see if someone comes to the
dharm as newcomer or also afterwards
with an attitude of openness in saying I
have my opinions like everyone has
but am I am
I um do I have
a a will
to to discuss or not to take what I have
as as opinion for granted and uh it's
like this and uh and I know it or or am
I am I available to hear other to hear
the noble ones who who have the a
knowledge which uh which has to be
acquired and I think this
is Al a very helpful point to recognize
if uh if we are uh able to let let go a
little bit of our
preconceived opinions so it is about
coming to terms with one's own views and
assumptions about oneself and the world
yes now when one adopts a scientific or
academic or scholarly attitudes which is
more or less the
same is can your own views and
assumptions come to light if you take an
objective stance if you are concerned with
stance if you are concerned with
it's about suffering isn't
it is is it about my existential
suffering you can't address that through
through the
scientific or Paradigm or scholarly
attitude no so the whole nature of human
existence of personal existence is fully
outside the scope of the scientific
domain so we're not saying that there's
anything wrong with science it's just
that that the Dharma is outside of the
phenomena that science
investigates and someone's own views and
assumptions are not publicly observable
for example and yet the whole practice
begins in a sense by coming to terms
with one's own views and assumptions
about the world putting them next to how
the noble ones regard things and then
the question becomes am I regarding
things the way Ordinary People do or am
I regarding things the way the noble
ones do and if you find a discrepancy
there then the question is why do you
hold on to the way Ordinary People
regard things because if that would be
right you wouldn't suffer but if you
wouldn't suffer then what's the point of
view the discourses so there is a
question of coming to terms with one's
own View and let's say substituting that
those views for the right views that we
are saying are reflected in the
discourses and there's nothing
scientific about that yeah that's what
is defining whether the attitude is
authentic or not is whether it pertains
to suffering and that's yeah and that's
a subjective reference point yeah which
the Buddha kept all the way if the
Buddha would have been a scientist you
would never have become the Buddha
that's a contradiction he kept asking
himself am I still liable to suffering
if this happens if that happens then
would that still affect my mind and and
when the answer is yes there are still
things that can disturb my mind he would
not declare full complete Awakening
that's a completely subjective reference
point and so that has to be established
from the outset because otherwise once
whole frame of reference as you put it
is just going to be or as you put it
actually it's going to be misinterpreted
and then it's like well I interpreted
like this and I interpreted like that
but in the end the dhama is seen
individually by those who are
wise so then there's no question of
different inter a it either
resolves the existential burden which
isuka or
doesn't so then in addition to certain
kinds of discourses that are worth well
perhaps looking into first but is of
equal importance or perhaps even more
important actually is to approach the
discourses with the right attitude and
we have said so far that the attitude is
to not assume that one is understood but
has not been understood and secondly to
cont deter with one's own views and
opinions and put them next to what one
reads in the discourses and then be
honest with oneself am I regarding
things the way the no ones do or
not am I suffering am I liable to
suffering am I still liable to suffering
and if that is the attitude and somebody
is transparent and
honest then does it in the end really
matter what kind of sutas they read no I
mean the most
of the biku I mean they didn't no none
of the B had access to the nikayas
during the time of the Buddha I mean
they they would have many of them would
have had you know only a few interactions
had you know only a few interactions
with the Buddha or with his
disciples yeah yeah so that's the other
thing actually the goal is not to to to
read all the discourses or translate all
of them or learn them all by heart
because in fact most people even Arabs
did not NE necessarily here all the
Buddhist teaching so you know it's
better to fully understand and see all
the implications of a few discourses
then to have knowledge of all of them
but not see anything directly for
yourself now how many discourses
nowadays people need to reflect upon in
order for the Right View to land will of
course differ from Individual to
individual and in a sense it's a very
rich situation that all the discourses
are there but we should not conflate or
newcomer should not conflate the idea
that it is about accumulating knowledge
because that's just more desire it's
about actually
understanding the the original question
and the answers that I recorded in those
discourses now if we have said all of
this to a
newcomer right to somebody who comes
here and says where to begin with the
discourses then have we come up with a
sufficient answer
or is there anything more that we should
say maybe uh hear the discourses or uh
read the discourses is one thing but
also uh hearing the Dharma from from
someone in which one can have a
confidence is also very very helpful or
maybe watching yes
watching some uh leaving
people speaking about
it can also help in yeah in addiction of
in in more or how can I say
complimentary to reading the text and
and just uh coming to terms with them by
by oneself
yeah because texts don't speak back to
you and they don't say whether you've
interpreted them rightly or not and so
there's perhaps a third category of
discourses that we that we can briefly
mention right in addition to the ones
where somebody breaks through to dama
and that stock phrase that contrasts
ordinary people with the noble ones
there also a collection of discourses
where the factors for the rising
override view are being
discussed and and if gaining the right
view is the most important thing that
the new comer should look out for then
to be aware what the factors for the
arising of Right View are is obviously
of key
importance right and one of the factors
for that view is hearing
to which obviously means that if
somebody is talking about it they are
iao or Noble
deciple and one needs to attend to those
teachings widely which is the Y Manar
but that deserves a all separate
discussion so I suggest we don't go into
that just now but those are the two
factors for theising of Right View and
this is sometimes further elaborated
upon by saying that you know to hang out
with those people who are already over
right view is greatly
beneficial so there's
that as well but you know if somebody
has no knowledge of the discourses how
are they ever going to recognize whether
somebody else is presenting the Buddha's
teaching rightly you see that's going to be a
rightly you see that's going to be a
difficulty so even if one wants to
follow someone else out of
faith I would still say that it is
better to also make an effort to become
familiar with the payas just to make
sure that you're putting that you're
placing your faith rightly because if
you're are following someone who doesn't
know what they're talking about then you
can basically spend the rest of your
life practicing things that do not bring
right results you cannot start blaming
the other person because you are the one
who decided to put your faith
there [Music]
[Music]
what what El what do you say yeah
it's sometimes it seems to me it's it's
really also really it's a it's also a
kind of
uh yeah it's kind of uh how can I say
um it's not easy how can one be sure
okay following this uh this
interpretation I I will uh yes I will go the the way
I I will uh yes I will go the the way
which I will afterwards after having
explored and and investigated find the
right or or
not what you say about read learning the
p or uh is this what you you no I didn't
say learning the P I said reading the P
reading the P which can be in a
translation with yeah the suas the sutas
yes yes and uh and so what then to look
for in someone else do the discourses
say anything about that are there
qualities that give at least some
indication that someone might know what
they're talking
about
perhaps you can conclude our discussion
by clearing that up if there are some
indications like I
mean um one doesn't really know whether
somebody else has it until you yourself
have it and even then where discour is
where ARS don't recognize other ARS but
okay being an Arad that's not really an
issue but you know so how are you going
to recognize whether somebody else knows
what they're talking about can can can
we come up with some indication some
things that at least point in the right
direction well it always has to be
rooted in this uh this authenticity that
we talked about and responsibility in
terms of really am I liable to suffering
and is this helping me to to come out of
my liability to suffering is this
teaching helping me mhm um without that
authenticity then that
then that
is yeah it's impossible I mean it's so
easy to follow somebody because they're
charismatic or they look confident or
um because because there's so many other
people following
them or all sorts of reasons um but this
criteria of am I suffering am I liable
to
suffering is
um is what the Buddha was pointing to uh
what his entire teaching is contained
within um yeah so following someone's
instruction and then checking for
oneself whether one's suffering
diminishes that is how you can see if
you're moving in the right direction but
you see we are still talking one step back
see we are still talking one step back
like where to where to put your faith so
if somebody doesn't even observe let's
say five or eight precepts is it is it
worth is it worth well listening to
someone like that no yeah good good
point point to yeah what is always said
to to start with the with the Sila with
the restraint but there also it needs an
understanding to to to make a reason why
why is this a let's say a prerequisite
sure that understanding can follow but
that's of course never going to happen
if you are starting if you're listening
to someone who himself or herself
doesn't even follow these basic precepts
right is seclusion a factor if
somebody's always surrounded by other
people yes is that a good indication or
not yeah that's also
criteria and then as the suas say um you
have to get to know someone not like on
a personal intimate level that's not
what was meant but it takes for this
authentic attitude that you were
referring to that's not so easy to
discern if you just meet someone for the
first time so it takes some time with someone
time so it takes some time with someone
or to regularly see someone in in order
to find out if if you can catch a
glimpse of that attitudes it's not just
once or twice or in public occasions and
as we see so often then behind the scene
you know all the scandals and the and
the misdemeanors come to the service but
publicly it can all look great um so you
know one wants to be careful with that
so we're talking about precepts sense
restraint seclusion and look for an
attitude of authenticity honesty and
people themselves being serious about
that and
perhaps everything else is up to the
individual and to resolve their own
doubts which are going to be there
anyway until they
not well that's a that could be
misleading in the sense of
um no no I I mean subjectively right
doesn't Noble disciple have doubt about
what is dhama no right so um so since
the whole goal is to see
Dharma then there will always be
doubt about what dhama is and what dhama
is not and whether somebody else is
perhaps speaking in the cor with them or
not until one sees for oneself right
what did you mean something else um just
yeah no it just maybe could have been
interpreted that the sort
of yeah that doubt is something that one
could um in a
way encourage or yeah
um but that's not what you meant
obviously you disqualified it by saying
but um yeah the attitude that towards
doubt and yeah is to see it as doubt and
not to get absorbed in the content of
the doubt obviously yes and but that's
uh to recognize doubt as a phenomena
will be necessary in order to abandon
doubt yeah and but that will be in the
end up to the individual practitioner
that's not going to be external
circumstances re resolving that and that
will already be part of looking at one's
own mind and taking one's whole attitude
subjectively I I would be careful with
the word introspection by the way which
you used earlier um I I don't think I
would use it like that but to to keep
the subjective perspective and to
realize that doubt is also part of
suffering and that it is and that it is
an aspect of of seeing things rightly
that there can't be any any any doubt
about it
right one other thing that I found
interesting to look for in perspective
teacher is their emphasis on personal
is their emphasis on personal
responsibility so is this teacher
somebody who is trying to teach you how
to be independent of them
uhuh uh a good
teacher doesn't want their students to
call them up every time they have a
question a good teacher wants to teach
the material so that those students can
become independent in their
understanding of it
so yeah so a noble disciple is
independent of others in his
understanding so if a teacher is setting
himself up in a way that students only
become more dependent on his teaching or
his organization or his methods or
technique that should already be a big
red
flag yeah it's another Factor quite
right there are no uh no secret
stages there are no secrets no secret
stages in the teaching ah there's no
secrecy that's now the other thing
people who want to belong to something
special to something
exclusive that they might be drawn in by
taking special vows and do preliminary
practices and become part of something
secret or esoteric is there any such
aspect in the early Buddhist
teaching no so the Buddha himself
explicitly said that there's nothing
held back in the closed closed Fist of
the teacher so the dhama from that point
of view is accessible and apparent here
now which doesn't mean publicly
observable but it is apparent here and
now unaccessible so anyone who says join
my secret Club should be another big red
flag quite
right any other factors
well I think
um going back to the
sutas they have
a consistent framework or or context or
understanding of all the suitors that
every single
sutor it's not like um one sutor saying
one thing the other suit is saying
another thing yeah there there is this
consistent um
understanding which
enables every Suitor to be easily
understood in in the sense is effortless
because because they they abide in this
understanding that yeah incorporates corporates all
that yeah incorporates corporates all
the suits yeah incorporates right so D
phenomena yes so Dharma is not bchw work
it's it's not like oh we've got some
people who who have understood this
collection of this courses but there's a
separate sect that has understood those
kind discourses we're saying that D is
One Vision yeah and so somebody should
be capable of at least pointing out if
you can put it like that um that which
all the discourses have in common so to
speak yeah so they might never have had
certain words but then if if it's
explained to them they're oh yeah that's
what you mean oh yeah yeah so so it's
not like they have this sort of um
eological you know knowledge of or
information they just have this
understanding which enables them to yeah
to to which incorporates all phenomena
possible yeah so it's about the meaning
and not just about the phrasing even
though phrasing plays its part we're not
going to have quarrels back and forth
about phrasing as such it's important
that somebody can explain in their own
terms the meaning of suffering exactly
to get out yeah so that's what all
discourses have in common suffering and
the ending of suffering if somebody has
that reference
point then doesn't really matter which
sutas they begin with in the end if the
attitude is right then every discourse
should point in the same direction might
do so to different degrees or it might
stop a bit earlier and doesn't go all
the way but they should all go in the
same direction and that's what one wants
to become familiar with with that
direction where suffering ceases and
then to just work on
it
yes